In the last lesson, we looked at how
to improve retrieval results
by augmenting the query
we send with an LLM.
In this lesson, we're going to use a
technique called cross-encoder re-ranking to score
the relevancy of our retrieved results
for the query that we sent.
Let's dig in.
Re-ranking is a way to
order results and score
them according to their
relevancy to a particular
query.
So let's take a look at
how this works underneath.
In re-ranking, after
you retrieve results for
a particular query, you
pass these results along with
your query to a re-ranking model.
This allows you to re-rank the output
so the most relevant
results have the highest
rank. Another way to
think about this is
your re-ranking model scores each
of the results conditioned on the
query, and those with the
highest score are the most
relevant.
Then you can just
select the top ranking
results as the most
relevant to your particular query.
So let's take a look at how
to do this in practice.
First, we import our
helper functions as before.
And we load the data into Chroma.
So one use of re-ranking is to get more
information out of the
long tail of query results.
So let's
take a look at this query that we've already
covered once before, which is
what has been the investment in
research and development.
And usually we've been asking
for five results in
return for our particular
query, but now we're
gonna ask for 10.
That means we're gonna get a longer tail
of possibly useful results. And
again, we're gonna include documents and
embeddings. And so
let's retrieve the
documents and taking a look at
what we get, we see that
we get the same first five results as
before because retrieval is
deterministic, but we also
have five new results, which might have
relevant information to our
question. The trick is
to figure out which of these
results are actually relevant to our
specific query instead
of just being
the nearest neighbors in embedding space.
And the way
we do that is through
using a cross-encoder re-ranking. So we're
going to use the sentence
transformers cross-encoder, and we're
going to instantiate it
with a particular
model.
So what is a cross-encoder model?
Sentence transformers are made up
of two kinds of models. There's
something called a Bi-encoder, where a
Bi-encoder encodes queries
separately, and then we
can use the output of
those Bi-encoders to perform cosine
similarity and find
the nearest neighbors.
In contrast, a BERT
cross-encoder takes both our query
and our document and passes it
through a classifier which outputs a
score.
And in this way,
we can use our cross-encoder
to score our
retrieved results by
passing our query and each retrieved
document and scoring
them using the cross-encoder. We
can use the cross-encoder by passing
in the original query and each
one of the retrieved documents and
using the resulting
score as a relevancy or ranking
score for our retrieved results.
So we've
instantiated our cross encoder. And
the first thing we're going
to do is create pairs.
The pairs consist of
our query and each
doc in our retrieved documents.
And we're just going to ask the cross
encoder to score each pair.
So let's print out our scores.
And while we see that
the first two documents have
high scores for our query,
we notice first of
all that the second
retrieved document is actually
a much higher score
than our first one. And also some
documents in the longer tail of
retrieved results have
higher scores than some of the
documents in the first five.
So what would that look like if we
were to reorder our
documents according to score?
We see that the second
document is now ranked first.
First document is ranked second.
And something in the long
tail actually makes it into
the top five and in
fact the top five re-ranked
results contain results
that are originally
the sixth and
seventh results while
the fourth and fifth results are
actually ranked quite low.
So in this way we've used the cross-encoder and
the score that it
produces to re-rank our results,
and now if
we were to cut to this
top five we'd see that the
results should be much
more relevant than what
we had before because
we've mined more of the
long tail for information that's
actually relevant to our question.
Now you might already see where I'm
going with this.
But given the number
of results that we
get with query expansion
and the way in
which each generated query
addresses a different part
of the complex question,
we can use the cross-encoder re-ranker technique
to actually get
all of the best results for
the original query from the augmented
expanded queries instead
of just sending all of them
to the LLM. And here's how we
do that.
So from the previous lab,
this is just our original
query and the generated queries.
And I've
saved them into text here for you. And
then we do the same thing.
We concatenate the
original and generated
queries together and
we retrieve the results.
And then, as last time,
we deduplicate the retrieved results.
And now we create pairs,
just as we did in the previous example,
where we make pairs
of the original query
and each retrieved document.
In this way, we can compute the
relevancy of the retrieved
results for the augmented
queries to the original
query and select among
them the five best
that we actually want
to pass to the LLM. So let's
create those pairs and let's score
them.
And one great thing about using a cross-encoder
model like this one is it's extremely
lightweight and runs
completely locally.
So here are the scores
of all of our retrieved results.
And we can use these
scores to order our results
and give us a new ordering.
And then we can pass the
top five of these new results
to the LLM and get the
most relevant information
from this long tail of queries
that we got through query expansion
and the retrieved results for our
augmented queries.
So, in this lab,
we learned how to use a cross-encoder
as a re-ranking model, and we've
seen how we can apply re-ranking both to get
more out of the long tail of a
single query, as well as to
filter the results of an augmented
expanded query to
only the results
relevant to the original query itself.
This is a really
powerful technique and worth
experimenting with some more.
And it's a good
idea to try to understand and get
an intuition for how the
re-ranking score might change depending on
query, even when
the result that your
retrieval system is giving
you are the same.
This is because the cross-encoder re-ranker
can emphasize different parts of
the query
than the embedding model
does.
And so the ranking that it
provides is much
more conditional on
the specific query than just what
is naively returned
by the retrieval system itself.
In the next lab, we'll
talk about query adapters.
Query adapters are a way to
directly alter or augment the query
embedding itself using
user feedback or other types of
data to get better query results.